all right well Hey listen everybody
thanks for coming really appreciate you
all joining us here as those of you who
might be watching this by video can tell
we're doing our usada CEO message which
we do once a quarter once a month just
depending on the news that's going on we
decided to do a little bit different
today we've got some people from the
staff who were kind enough to come in
and hopefully ask some questions near
the end of this but we thought we would
take some time to talk about the TMZ
China positive tests and how they were
handled and really dive into some of the
facts we're going to also for this
discussion have sections um so if you're
watching on TV by video whether you're
an elite level athlete that this will go
out to or you're someone you know maybe
in a sport organization or maybe you sit
at the W governing boards or government
um organization that deals with
anti-doping the idea is that you can
fast forward you can watch continuously
if you hope to or need to um but you can
also split it up and come back to it as
your time permits but you know given
that so much has been written about this
topic the Chinese 23 TMZ positive test
literally we went and counted all the
words from the various press conferences
and the statements that wada has put out
and it's over 40,000 words and if you're
curious that translates into somewhere
between 160 in in 200 Pages um the
problem is many of the questions that we
began initially asking when this news
first broke we we just simply don't have
answers to and that's exactly why we
wanted to try to do this forum so that
people could remember what those
questions are and and continue our best
to try to get answers to those questions
let me just say that we've asked also
wada to sit down with us unfortunately
they've refused to do that and I think
as many of you have seen from the Press
statements you know when we began asking
questions when the initial reports were
um publicized by the various media
departments and and Outlets you know W
went on the attack and part of their
strategy I think was intentionally to
deflect away from answering some of the
basic questions and try to shift you
know the mudslinging so to speak onto
those who were asking the questions
sometimes to us at usada and us
personally
um sometimes other organizations you
know of course we're going to defend our
honor and our duty and our integrity and
what we are here to do on behalf of
clean athletes and so you see some of
this back and forth from a press
standpoint and and really that has just
gotten in the way of getting to the
bottom of what actually happened in
these cases and how can we answer the
questions that we're having from clean
athletes um here both in the United
States but also around the world so a
few things we're going to go go through
number one why do we care number two
what do we know at this point number
three what do the rules say number four
what does the science say number five
what does the investigation say and then
lastly we're going to talk a little bit
about where we are now and where do we
go from here and and really what a clean
athletes you know need and what does the
public need to move on from this
situation so why do we care I think
number one you have to look at the world
anti-doping code it's the set of rules
that apply to all of us um around the
world those who participate in the
Olympic movement and you see in the in
the writing and the pre Preamble of what
the code is all about is this idea that
the code is here to promote free sport
and thus promote Health fairness and
equality and and we really believe here
at usada that one of the biggest
injustices that can happen to an athlete
is for them to be robbed
by another athlete who is not playing by
the rules and it's this set of rules
that sets that framework for those
athletes to compete the right way and
gives them hope that their sacrifice
their hard work is actually going to be
rewarded when they show up at an
international competition or a national
competition where these rules apply and
let me just make one point and you've
heard other athletes talk about this for
those maybe who are watching this that
aren't in the registered testing pool of
course staff is fully aware of this it
is awfully difficult to live
successfully as a clean athlete in the
anti-doping program just think about it
for a second and if you're not familiar
with it it might shock you what our
athletes have to go through in order to
live successfully in the anti-doping
system they they have to literally give
us their whereabouts their location 365
days a year so that they can be located
for testing if you decide hey I I'm
going to sleep in this morning I don't
feel like going to the track or the
swimming pool whatever area you're going
to train at 8:00 you want to sleep in
and go at 9: well before you fall back
asleep you better make sure you change
your whereabouts it's it's pretty
incredible I'm not sure any other
industry has people other than maybe
Parolees or people that have been
convicted of crimes literally maybe
airplane pilots maybe you know railroad
car driver who are tested but it but
it's an incredible system that athletes
have to abide by and and then think
about what happens when they do show up
and test you a stranger literally knocks
on your door at 6:00 a.m. in the morning
potentially or maybe at 10:00 at night
after your kids have already gone to bed
and you're trying to go to sleep
yourself imagine a loud P pounding on
your door or a doorbell ringing at that
time of the night and a stranger is
there to collect a
sample and and what happens when they
collect the sample I mean again we all
know here in the in the room you
literally have to pull down your
pants and show your genitals in front of
a stranger and provide a sample in a
cup holy cow what we're asking of
athletes and and if it's not a urine
sample then they get a needle and they
stick a needle in your vein and take
your blood and in order to ship it off
to the laboratory this is what we're
expecting of our our Elite level
athletes it it's actually pretty
incredible that they're willing to do
this we could talk about whether they
have a choice and The Leverage to have
it done in the way that it's done but
the fact is this is the life they have
to live and and not only that they have
to worry about things they take their
medications any vitamins or minerals or
potential
supplements it is an incredibly
difficult life to have to live and and
what our athletes tell us
resoundingly is yes this is the rules
and yes we're willing to do this it's
crazy to think that we have to do this
but it's way less inconvenient it's way
less intrusive than going to a major
national competition or a major
International competition like the
Olympic Games and getting robbed by
someone who is not Abiding and playing
by those same
rules and they want consistency in the
application of the rules and ensure that
around the world every athlete is held
to the same rules that they're held to
and this strenuous system that's the
least that we can do so so we care on
behalf of those athletes that are held
to those standards and there are many
around the world that are held to those
standards but but athletes themselves
care here you see a picture from Adam
Petey a UK swimmer one of the top
swimmers in the world out of England and
you see him he cares because it's fraud
on the people he competes against if
someone is cheating him and it's also
fraud on the public for those who are
watching him here someone uh Olympic
swimmer from Australia many of you know
the name Zach um cook similarly it's
incredibly disappointing to know that
other athletes haven't been held to the
same rules and the same process that's
required on on all athletes and of
course in this particular case the TMZ
cases a athletes are asking the
questions this was at a press conference
in Paris when one of the top swimmers
said we have not had the answers
answered that we need the questions
answered that we need answered we need
to
hear so what do we
know well we know because the media
exposed it not because the rules were
followed that otherwise should have
reported it but the media in April of
this year 2024 disclosed that there were
there were actually 28 positive tests on
23 swimming athletes a lead of the elite
from China from an event January 1 to
January 3 of 2021 and I mentioned there
28 positive tests and that's going to be
important a little bit later in the
conversation because some athletes had
multiple tests and multiple positive
tests and we'll talk a little bit about
that in a second the positive test were
for a prohibited drug under the world
anti-doping agency's rules the
prohibited list you can look at the
prohibited list yourself and see it it's
called triodine or what's known as TMZ
and I'm just going to use it as TMZ for
purposes of this conversation but really
importantly TMZ is tested for and is
prohibited in competition so at the
event itself as well as all times so
outside of the event itself and there's
a particular ular reason for that
because TMZ is one it was a controlled
substance only available by prescription
does not come in food does not show up
in kitchens without a reason it's was
originally developed as an angina drug
it helps your cardiac function well we
also know and the reason it's prohibited
out of competition is because it helps
reduce fatigue and it gives your cardiac
um efficiency when you're training so
the recovery and the training that you
would experience if you're using this
would would be enhanced so while it may
not and you're going to hear a little
bit later that wada has really focused
on that it didn't have performance
enhancing benefits at low levels during
the competition and we're going to talk
a little bit about that what question
we've asked what about the benefits if
it was intentionally used prior to the
competition if you can train harder and
longer if you can recover faster and
more efficiently
that's an ideal drug to use when you're
training and that is why it's prohibited
all the time it's also why the default
sanction for it is four years it's the
highest maximum level of four years for
an offense for
it so what do the rules
say very quickly the water code again
that document that I put up at the very
beginning is the rules we're talking
about and you can find it there's
booklets floating around you can go on
the internet and look at the rules
yourself I've made some sites to the
rules um that I would hope you would go
and check um but the water rules have
what's known as strict liability a lot a
lot of people you know strict liability
in most countries is basically what
happens when you get pulled over first
speeding and the idea is you would never
be able to prove someone knowingly or
intentionally broke the speed limit
because when the officer came to your
door to get give you a ticket you would
just say oh I didn't know I was going
over the speed limit and that that
intent to speed would never be able to
be proven and so what you see in the
anti-doping landscape is the exact same
idea of what's known as strict liability
and what it means is when you have a
positive test the burden to prove that
you didn't intend to do it shifts to you
we assume
intent and so again we're talking TMZ
here's just a small graph to demonstrate
this article 21 of the W code assumes
that you
intentionally did and used for
performance- enhancing purposes if you
have a positive drug test for in this
case
TMZ that's all that is
needed and once that is
demonstrated there's an automatic
provisional suspension for TMZ and just
a a small note here because there's been
a lot of conversation around provisional
suspensions you can see article 74 from
the water code is cited this drug again
because of its powerful performance
enhancement both in competition and out
of competition it requires a mandatory
provisional suspension some drugs there
is not a mandatory and and the idea
there is if you're going to get a
lasting benefit from a particular drug
you want the person immediately off the
playing field if the drug is not going
to give you a lasting benefit then then
it's okay if they compete a few weeks
later until the case is resolved the way
in a TMZ case a positive for TMZ that
you can undo the provisional suspension
is by going to a hearing and the athlete
has to demonstrate a contaminated
product there is an exception at a
hearing in front of an independent
hearing officer the athlete has to
demonstrate that a contaminated product
and look the contaminated product has a
definition and it is a product that has
a label that the athlete couldn't
identify had the substance in it it it
doesn't imp it doesn't apply on its face
please read the rule doesn't apply to
environmental contamination or food
contamination or a drug showing up in a
kitchen magically it just simply doesn't
apply and worse here what we now know is
that the Chinese athletes weren't even
notified of the positive tests
they didn't know about the positive
tests so they had no way to appeal the
provisional suspension and look it's a
it's a minor point but if those athletes
would have been provisionally suspended
as the rules required they would have at
a minimum been out of competition until
June of 2021 when China the Chinese
anti-doping agency resolved the cases
they would have missed their Olympic
trials other athletes who should have
gotten the benefit benefit of those
rules would have you know been at those
Olympic trials made the Olympic team so
there were Chinese athletes that got
disadvantaged by the rules that require
all to to be applied in every case were
not
applied number three there's an
automatic violation there is no such
thing as no
violation in the water code once you
have an adverse analytical finding a
positive test for TMZ it cannot just
simply go away that's article one
article nine automatic
disqualification from the Advent at
which you test positive it's automatic
there is there is no discretion it's
it's unauthorized it's illegal under the
rules to say that you're not going to
disqualify and again I I I think we have
to care about those Chinese athletes who
lost their placement at the event
January 1 through January 3 they should
have been increased in the standings
they should have gotten the money that
went along with their victories cuz the
people in front of them that had the
positive test absolutely under the rules
should have been disqualified and and
those athletes got taken advantage of
when the rules weren't applied fairly
and evenly how much money I I don't know
was it points think of the confidence
you gain when you win an event um
bringing home a trophy to your parents
how nice would that have been no I was
absolutely taken away from those
athletes
there's also a default sanction of four
years and again article 102 of the water
code Public
Announcement automatic in a case you can
look at article
14.3 so that is strict liability what
happens the only time that there's a
difference in that outcome is when the
athlete proves
that first
section
proves that the positive test was due to
no significant fault or no fault of
their own so again the burden shifts to
the athlete the athlete under the rules
has to prove it and if they can prove no
significant fault or no fault in how the
violation occurred then they can get a
reduction which we'll talk about in just
a second very important ly in order to
prove no significant fault or no fault
the athlete has to prove the source of
the positive
test so they have to demonstrate where
the positive came from
basically and in addition to that and
that's in the rules that's in the
definition of no fault or no significant
Fault In The Water code there's a whole
definition section you can go and look
at the actual definitions of it and this
is this is common practice for those of
us in anti-doping everyone knows these
rules that handles these cases as we
move cases forward the second point
is you also have to prove causation
meaning that the source that you proved
cause the positive test actually then
call the level of the finding that it
correlates to the level of the finding
in your sample now there is a little bit
of debate some lawyers some cast panels
say you causation yeah you don't really
have to prove it but recent case and
certainly W's position is that you have
to prove that causation so there's
really two elements that you have to
prove moving forward but let me make one
last Point even if you prove that the
only thing that changes is this fouryear
sanction can go down to zero sanction
could be one year could be two years but
it can be reduced if you prove no
significant fault the source and the
contamination however the automatic
violation Remains the disqualification
remains and the Public Announcement
remains and even if you
believe there was no fault which is what
W has said and even if you believe they
proved the source and that they proved
cause ation you still have a public
announcement a disqualification and a
violation and that was not done China
didn't do it and W allowed China not to
do it so what does the science say is it
contamination is it a no fault case W
has said it's a no fault case and here's
a statement from W that they ran and
they've said different variations of
this same comment which is basically
compelling scientific evidence pointed
exclusively to the fact that this was a
case of no fault
contamination so w is saying in their
view the facts that they saw proved that
prior slide that I showed that this was
a no fa contamination case they've had
different variations but that's
basically the point that all you have to
look at is the science to determine that
this was a no fault contamination case
so let's take a little bit of a look at
the science you see in while not in
necessarily in their press conf ments
when the US Congress did ask for very
poignant information about this
contamination Theory and why wada
thought and believed it was a
contamination no fault case W's lawyers
responded and and you can go and look at
the letter and they basically had a few
points of why from a scientific
standpoint they believe this was a no fa
contamination case number one swimmers
tested positive at the same time time at
low
levels okay so swimmers tested positive
at the same time at low
levels look we handled the Lance
Armstrong case the US Postal Services
case and and there were teams that ED
drugs together they stayed at the same
hotels and did blood transfusions in the
hotels I don't that's not really um a
fact that weighs towards contamination
or not but but it's one of the facts
they indicated they also said there was
no performance enhancing benefit at the
competition and and really importantly
the Nuance that I think they're trying
to draw here is that at low levels at
the event maybe that competition itself
that day was not impacted by the low
levels however as we previously
discussed the training benefits the
recovery benefits if you can be rested
and refreshed and more efficient
recovery coming into an event and you
able to train harder before that event
well of course that's going to transfer
over to the event and give you a
performance Advantage during that event
and again it's why the substance is
prohibited all the time if it didn't
give you that Advantage then it only
should be prohibited in competition and
and we're talking about a wholly
different thing here if that's the case
but but that's not the case so number
two variations in results they use the
word 10 to rule out deliberate ingestion
um yeah ingestion so language is
slightly different it tends to not
exclusively like we heard previously on
the slide but it but it tends
to and what they're talking about here
and I'm going to dive into this a little
bit because it's the main thrust I think
of their scientific position which is
the athletes had I mentioned there were
28 positives some had multiple well you
see some of the athletes had a negative
positive so on one day of the event they
had a negative sample the next day they
had a positive sample some had positive
negative positive and then there was
some that had a negative negative
positive and and what's position is
let's just take the the negative
positive so negative meaning they didn't
they hadn't used it they hadn't been
exposed to it and then the next day when
they're tested actually they were
positive for it that's the thrust of
what their scientific argument is and
we're going to talk a little bit about
that in a second number what is now
number three um swimmers from different
regions of China had different coaches
again that if that fact is
true um it it really has no bearing on
the science and what's been reported
just in the last month or so is that
there are serious questions if in fact
that's true what's actually been
reported by media that whistleblowers
have brought to Media is that in fact no
the swimmers were together most of the
time training prior to this event um the
third actually the fourth same place at
the same time when the positives happen
kind of address that a little bit
already and then three other Swimmers at
a different Hotel tested
negative again not scientific but facts
that help you know Lind in their mind
but again we don't know how many
Swimmers at this hotel tested
negative which is a fact that's worth
considering as well if you're going to
consider how many at other hotels but
you also so as the Lance Armstrong
example indicated you stay together
sometimes you dope together um you don't
stay together maybe you're not doping
together again is it definitive of uh
contamination noal I I I think not but
that's what W has indicated so to dive a
little bit into the two elements of the
science this is an excretion graph and
and I'm going to focus on their position
about variations at this point
and what you have here this is days okay
so let's say you take a drug and you see
that drug this is the concentration of
the prohibited substance that drug goes
up in your body and if you were to
provide a sample it would be high and
then over time it eventually leaves your
body certain drugs can stay in your body
for many days many weeks many months
some depends on how much you take how
long you've been using there are other
drugs and think about if you take an
Advil right which is not prohibited but
if you take an Advil the doctor will
tell you you know take some three three
or four hours later because it wears off
and as it wears off it's also going to
leave your system that's the nature of
that type of
drug um there is also what's known as a
limit of detection so we understand
what's been reported is that limit of
detection for TMZ is about 100
picograms and so that's the level which
below that level the lab cannot detect
it it very well could be in your urine
you just can't detect it so when you use
the term negative yes technically it's
declared negative but that drug could
still be in your urine just below what
the lab is able to
detect Well w talks about again the
variations and we talked about that
negative positive negative or positive
NE negative positive um this is what
they're talking
about which is and we've just made this
graph you see at low ends of the
excretion curve near the level of
detection you very well may see above
the level of detection the next one
below the next one above this is a
common phenomenon in anti-doping science
we we know this there are many drugs
that this happens with you can look at
the M3 of oral tabol you can look at
chopine you can look at ostarine or any
of the sarms it it is a known phenomenon
because the the urine will have
different parts to it that can help or
deter your ability to detect it at or
below the level of detection and so it's
It's Perfectly Normal sometimes that you
have these fluctuations and these
variations and here here's a couple
reasons for these variations one is
specific gravity you know we've asked
for the data on these samples um W could
put the data out there if they chose to
you know they've made statements that
the specific gravity in most of the
cases was normal but but we don't know
and we also don't know what were the
characteristics of the sample and and
for the athletes at home you you know
specific gravity is important because we
do subsequent samples you might you may
have to stay longer to testing because
we get another sample because it's based
on the P the specific gravity to make
sure we get a sample that can be
identified and that we need more urine
if it's you know dilute and not
concentrated enough there's other issues
bacterial degradation what what's
interesting in this case is these
samples um were it took two months
roughly and I think what w and China
have indicated is that was due to co
restrictions and hopefully they froze
them during that time period because
that helps the stability and avoids some
degradation but but we don't know how
much degradation and the point here is
the sample can fluctuate in its values
based on the sample storage and possible
degradation and of course there's
exercise and then I just mentioned the
stability if you're freezing or not
freezing the sample all right so that's
that's one the main thrust of their
argument on the variation and and
scientists who have seen this and I'm
not a scientist clearly I've consulted
with our science team we've talked to
others who have seen the science put out
by W and and this this is the best case
for W on the variation um and and it and
it's not very strong I don't think and
it's not very powerful um whatsoever
certainly doesn't prove exclusively
contamination it's just as consistent
with intentional use
and and we
know other substances this fluctuation
happens after intentional use at low
levels so shift your mind slightly to
look at this from a different
perspective now we want to look at well
is are these numbers consistent with
intentional
use and there's not a ton out there that
we've seen and W hasn't put much out
there on the rate at which if you take
TMZ intentionally the rate at which it
leaves your
body the best place to go is the case
the figure skater who by the way got
four
years um for a low level I think her
level is like 2.1 nanograms where we
understand these Chinese cases are 1.5
1.7 and Below best we can tell from some
of the reports we've again asked for
those specific numbers as well which
would be helpful to see um so we don't
know but here in val Eva you see that
wada was relying to the panel on
information provided by the manufacturer
TMZ and they've said in these Chinese
cases that they got confidential
information from the manufacturer that
helped them with their um determination
that this was a no fault contamination
case so if you look at this is again
verbatim from the valy Eva case what
they say is if an athlete uses 7.5
milligrams to 35 mg okay that the
concentration would end up being 1 nanog
to 1.7 n per milliliter after four or
five days does that does that make sense
so if you take it today four five days
later from now it's going to be at the
sample in your urine is going to be 1 to
1.7
nanograms so you got like a a 5day
window to use
it um they also say for lower doses okay
same
1.7 1 to 1.7 nanograms per milliliter
would be reached after 3
days so so one of the things we've asked
for we've asked W we've asked chinata
we've asked World Aquatics they've put
out a lot of information about all the
tests that the Chinese athletes were
doing well let's see what the testing in
December was and we know from the Ard
report the German documentary that was
one of the initial that broke this
that they claimed there was less testing
in the month of December on these
athletes and and it would be great to
know were there any tests on these
athletes two weeks before this event a
week before this event five days before
this event three days before this event
because I if the Chinese samples were at
let's say 1.5
1.6 in what the amount was in their
samples well that's exact
identical to if they would have used
this level dose three days
before so the questions around the
intentional use are alive and well and
athletes deserve to know here's just
that put you know on a
dosage five days that dose according to
the valy Ava panel based on water
science including the TMZ manufacturing
data is that after 5 days you'd be down
to 1 1 to 1.7 which is you know right at
the tail end of that excretion here's
the 0.5 7.5 dose again level of
detection down to that
level so a lot of people are familiar
that wada set up um self-appointed um
you know drafted the terms of reference
from the staffers who made the decision
not to appeal these cases which we
didn't think was the best best way to do
it it should have been done by the
executive committee to make sure that
this independent person katier and you
see the name right here above um that he
actually got to the material questions
that we all are hoping can have answers
to to satisfy clean athletes that why
the rules weren't followed and that in
fact this was some sort of contamination
and not intentional use and so I'm going
to walk through this report very briefly
and the annex which has a lot of
interesting facts and raises a lot of
interesting questions I put this in the
science section um equally could have
gone into other sections but please take
a look at it if you haven't seen it and
you know we could spend hours discussing
it but I but I think at the start there
were really two questions that were
asked and these are somewhat paraphrased
but I used tried to use the key language
um but you can look at the questions
yourself but but basically was there any
indication of bias towards China and W's
assessment of the decision ision by
chinata not to bring these cases forward
now wada has acknowledged and forums
that chinata did not follow the rules as
I taught previously in the legal section
they should have found a violation they
should have disqualified and they should
have made these publicly announced and
look if the transparency rule would have
been followed we're not having this
conversation the the problem is that for
whatever reason these were swept under
the carpet and the rules weren't
followed and we are now asking those
questions and we're starting to see
there's serious questions about were
these really contamination and why
wasn't it given the standard four-year
sanction that possibly should have been
given so that's the first question and
then the second question is based on the
case File and other elements that W had
at its disposal was W's decision not to
challenge the contamination Ser scenario
a reasonable one and again we just think
these two questions are entirely too
narrow and don't get to the heart of the
real issue a couple big points about
them I I think the first question
there's a there's a legal term it's
Latin called race ipol loquitor the
thing the thing speaks for
itself look China receives special
treatment under the rules like the bias
was towards China because the rules
didn't apply to China China as W has
acknowledged didn't apply the rules so
so of course they were biased towards
China it it's so obvious but you know of
course his answer was was a different
answer but but it seems to be pretty
obvious that when the rules aren't
applied to certain athletes in certain
countries like w failed to do in China
and yet in other countries they do apply
the rules and make it public and make
them prove Source before finding
contamination make them prove the
causation of The Source before finding
contamination that that they got
favorable treatment so so it's hard to
understand really at that level how they
came out to something different I I'll
also say a little bit more specifically
under article 71 of the wat
code what wat has talked about they had
zero or you know 100% chance of losing 0
percent chance of winning the cases if
they appealed the cases and and I think
they're really talking about the
contamination piece because because as
I've said already clearly 100% they win
that a violation committed that
disqualification should have happened
and they should have been made public
100% there there's no chance they would
have lost that because there is not the
ability under the rules there is no
authority to be able to do what China
did in these cases
but but I'd also say w had another
option that's clearly in the rules is
wada has the authority to basically
direct or
order an organization that has results
Management Authority on cases to fulfill
the results management
process and then and you can read the
rule and if that
organization doesn't do it they're found
non-compliant and they have to pay the
costs of whatever it would have cost for
someone else to bring the case what what
have failed to do that for some reason
and it's clear the athletes were never
notified they didn't bring these to a
hearing the results management process
as the rules required didn't happen and
yet W didn't direct or order as they
have the authority to do so Kier didn't
ask that question he didn't ask was it
reasonable that they didn't do this I
think clean athletes would say it wasn't
reasonable at all not to do that is what
is what I think would have been the
answer number two no appeal of the cases
for failure to follow the rules and
again it absolutely was reasonable to
appeal cases where the National
anti-doping Organization chinata didn't
have authority to do what they did and
and W we now know has admitted that they
didn't follow the rules and it certainly
would have been reasonable for them to
follow the rules and then and then
thirdly there was no compliance action
so when a National anti-doping
Organization and our staff we all know
this we've gone through an in-person
compliance audit in the last you know
end of 2022 and we know when they come
in they look at everything you've done
and every letter that you've sent and
make sure that you follow the letter of
the law and every case and every sample
um has to abide by the rules and the
procedures and if you don't do that they
bring a compliance case against you we
all remember the time and effort we put
in to that compliance audit they didn't
do that on chinata yet they knew chinata
didn't follow the rules and yet they
didn't use the tools that they had and
and that was not reasonable either the
the real
question that should have been asked and
a proper investigation into the handling
of this case and these cases should have
been did they do did w do everything
they should have done under the rules to
ensure that clean athletes rights were
upheld and it just it just is clear they
didn't so looking at the
annex of the ktia report and and
remembering what I said earlier about
the
contamination theory of water the
fluctuations a couple points I want to
make number one this is paragraph 33 of
the kti anex so again this is w a
self-review they interviewed some people
this was interviews with the science
department at w and and they had
uncertainties about the source of
contamination that's ktia based on
interviews now that remember that's
totally different than what the media
statement said right that I showed you
exclusively was the word pointed to well
actually at the time and during the ktia
review over the last couple months the
science folks didn't agree with that
they also said the lack of TMZ
measurements in a food stuff and I'm
going to talk a little bit about this in
just a second but the claim was that TMZ
was found in the kitchen and sauce
containers and in the kitchen Hub and
maybe in the sludge we don't know
exactly and it's a little bit vague in
the katier report but contrast that with
what they told Congress it was in the
kitchen Hub and the sludge and sauce
containers um but because they didn't
know the measurements in that stuff it
was almost impossible to design a
realistic scenario of how this could
have ended up in the urine remember that
causation you have to show that The
Source actually caused the level of the
positive for it to be a no fault
contamination case so the best that the
science team could do and again this is
all in paragraph 33 and I've taken out
some of the language that didn't
directly relevant but read the whole
piece please the results of the
calculations attempted to determine how
much contamination would you need to
cause the one to 1.7 nanogram finding in
the urine makes sense right like if you
eat a bunch of food that's contaminated
how much do you need to eat in order to
produce 1 to 1.7 nanograms in your urine
so they came to the conclusion a few
micrograms so just keep those thoughts
in your head for a second they also went
on to say that this was not sufficiently
precise to confirm or exclude
contamination
again this is this is the language that
kti after interviewing science team at w
put in his report highly different than
what we've seen so far they persisted in
finding that a few micrograms was high
for
contamination and was surprised that the
Chinese had not found someone actually
taking TMZ in the kitchen because that
few micrograms is a is a high amount
we're going to talk about that in just a
second so couple other questions that
come about from the ktia
annex first we know date-wise June 15
2021 China sent the files of the 28
positive test but the 23 athletes uh 13
of whom ended up being on the Olympic
team in
2021 11 of whom who had positive TMZ
tests end up being on the 20124 the most
recent Olympic games that just concluded
they send the file on June 15th 2021
well the very next day the W director
General has a phone call with the
Chinese minister of sport who also sits
on the W Foundation board and according
to the ktia report these cases come up
it's part of a conversation but the case
has come up and and it's awfully
interesting that the head of w is having
a conversation about these cases with
someone that sits on the W Foundation
board
on July 88th and you've heard W talk
about an outside legal opinion that was
given on July 8th they get an outside
legal opinion not to
appeal because they couldn't disprove
the contamination theory was essentially
of what they said well days after that
they get the initial science
information provided internally within
water so you know it's really
interesting that the outside legal
Council over you know a week before
roughly says don't appeal but yet they
didn't have the initial science
information so how how can you base a
recommendation not to appeal when you
don't have all the science
information number two Fina actually
appeals the
case on July 15th and what's interesting
is Fina had their expert report prior to
their decision to appeal they also had
the the the W legal report prior to them
appealing but they decided to go ahead
and appeal to Cass and really
interesting W has told its foundation
board that the two and the media and the
public that Fina and which is now World
Aquatics but Fina at the time and wada
were acting independently and they came
to the same conclusion separately but
the ktia report shows that that that's
just not right they were working very
very closely together in fact they were
talking about division of labor was the
quote in the katier report to determine
who was going to take what aspects of
the case but Fina actually
appealed they asked Cass to keep it
confidential pending what wada was going
to
do so on July 19th remember how I said
keep that few micrograms in your head
we're going to talk a little bit about
that for a second so the best that W
science team could get was it would take
a few
micrograms to equal to be contaminated
to equal the levels in the athletes
sample so they
ask in the in the annex the water legal
team asks China and writing um as it
reads how much contamination was in the
sauce containers and the kitchen and
what they said was there was a range
this is China's response back to water
back in in June July well July 19th is
when the response came back in so there
was 03 nanograms per
milliliter to or up to 0.2 nanograms per
milliliter in the sauce containers and
in the kitchen is what the Kate report
says and so that's that's point2 is the
maximum okay nanograms per milliliter
the maximum amount I'm just going to
focus on the maximum amount okay if it
was less less chance but let's just
focus on the maximum amount that they
reported and importantly that's
milliliters nanograms per milliliter so
it's measuring it in a liquid not a
solid but a but a liquid this actually
may be a typo you know our science folks
think it's probably a typo um because
you you know it's tough to measure
something off of sauce can or a kitchen
Hub um in a liquid form so it's it's
hard to know and and there and there was
one typo that was noted after the katier
report was published they made a
footnote that it had changed I don't
know we don't know but we're going to
analyze it under both just to just to be
sure so here if it is nanograms per
milliliter okay so think about it it's a
it's a liquid and 0 2 two nanog of that
milliliter are contaminated so the
question becomes in order to get a few
micrograms which again is the amount
that W has said you would have to take
to result in the positive test how many
how much of that liquid would you have
to actually
intake well 2 nanograms per milliliter
in order to get 1 microgram you'd have
to have 5,000 milliliters that are
contaminated which is 5
L which is 1.3
gallons so you'd have to have 1.3
gallons of a contaminated liquid to
equal one microgram that's one microgram
what do science said a few
micrograms so again just just so we're
clear and look we ran this by our
science people this morning I'm not the
scientist either but this this is
understandable and it makes no sense
that these athletes had
1.3 gallons of contaminated
liquid it's just it's it's hard to it's
hard to imagine so we our science folks
actually think this should be 0.3
nanograms per gram so again that's a
solid not a liquid but a solid and so if
it's contaminated the solid whether you
know if it's the sludge or the sauce or
the sauce container ERS but but let's
say it's a solid that's actually
contaminated
at 2 nanog per gr again we're taking the
maximum level similarly it would take
5,000
gram of that contaminated solid which is
kilg which is 11
PB so you'd have to eat 11 lounds of
whatever solid food was contaminated
with the MZ to equal the the one or a
few it's actually one it's the lowest
level the one
microgram it it it's it's incredible to
believe interestingly after W ran
assumably these kind of figures they
went back to China for clarification and
it's hard to tell in the ktia report but
China then says no Trace TMZ inside the
containers nor the food itself so they
kind of they kind of backed off it seems
again these are legit questions we have
but if you read the report and we've
read it in you know very very closely it
it seems to be that they backed off of
this and they said oh well you know that
happened to you know two and a half
months after ago we you know we we don't
know what the levels actually were and
they they came off of and and and
obviously they came off of it I would
suspect because it just doesn't add up
that this
contamination scenario happened and
remember what I said during the legal
part
causation there have been cast cases
where if the athlete can't prove the
actual amount of contamination found
resulted in the amount in the sample you
don't prove source for purposes a
finding of no
fault so then W science opinion comes in
that's July 3031 and there were two
different the chief science officer and
the director of science who both and I
and I read and I showed you the language
previously where they had uncertainties
they couldn't rule in or out
contamination that was their decision
however they
internally uh what a lawyer sent a note
internal lawyer sent a note around to
the staff saying we've closed the
case that's the gist of the case so last
section
what did the investigation
say because there's a lot of questions
did the athletes actually Stay Together
did were they in the same Hotel were
they training prior together were there
other athletes who stayed in that same
hotel that were tested that tested
negative did they look at the followup
you know the samples did they do B
samples did they look at lab
documentation did they investigate this
in the way that anti-doping
organizations are required to
investigate they did a a science review
we know that they've said that we've
seen a little bit of that in the ker
report so did they do an investigation
and and this might be the part that's
most troubling about this case because
you know we sent whistleblower tips in
March of 2020 to W's investigative and
intelligence team we sent more in
September of
2020 the ITA the international testing
agency also provided tips to W's inii
team we we know that kada has
acknowledged that we haven't seen um
what those tips are and then we sent a
further tip in April of 2023 and and the
gist of what we
provided was there that was the fact
that Chinese swimmers and the Chinese
National swim Association was doing two
things one hiding positive tests but
then also keeping their athletes away
from testing to avoid positive tests and
and that is an important fact we think
that correlates to the testing that
we've been asking for in that December
time period where at least one media
outlet has reported those swimmers had
way less testing in the month of
December leading into this event at
which they tested positive and so we've
asked for the dates of the testing on
those athletes to be published to give
us comfort that no this actually is a
case of contamination not of intentional
use but certainly the tips we got name
specific athletes that ended up having
positive tests talked about hiding them
from testing seems to correlate and be
directly Cooperative of this idea that
this is not contamination but it's
actually intentional
use what's even more
disturbing is that this is a this is a
report from the head of the
intelligence department at w and if you
look at the date it's May 15th
2020 so think about TimeWise this was
presented as we understand it to the W
executive committee it's a written
report that's now been
publicized that they they informed the
executive committee that they actually
did an investigation where there was a
Defector from China a doctor who had you
know information about systemic doping
within the sports community and that
they interviewed
Dr zuu I think is how you pronounce it
and they considered her to be a credible
witness this is a direct quote from that
report again that was presented on May
of 2020 just a few months before this
event and you know less than nine months
before w got first notice of 23 positive
tests for
TMZ they also said that some of the
allegations that this credible witness
Dr zuu Who they met with in Germany and
interviewed and turned into this report
some of the allegations were referring
to allegedly undetectable levels of
prohibited substances
namely
triodine andaz and growth
hormones so less than nine months before
they then get 28 positives on 23
athletes for low levels of
triodine they had just closed an
investigation
into um a whistleblower that they found
to be credible who told them this is
exactly what the Chinese swimmers and
athletes are doing in order to
dope and they even went so far to say
that should they receive new information
or evidence be presented we will reopen
the
case but but what we know unfortunately
is they didn't do whether based on this
or based this report this investigation
or based on the tips that we sent them
what we know is that when those 23
positives came in for TMZ that they
didn't open investigation they've
acknowledged they did a science review
maybe call it a science investigation
but their investigators did not do any
factual investigation into what actually
might have been going on so in fact wada
when these 28 positive samples again on
the 23 athletes came in what w actually
didn't open up a new investigation and
and here's what they said is one that
they looked into these files and I think
they're referring to the tips that us
and the ITA provided them when they said
this and that they logged those tips in
their
system which is
great they did advise after um hearing
from science and legal from what they
say and I think these comments are from
their press conference in in April of um
of this year I think it was April 22nd
that they did advise that there was no
impetus to investigate it it's hard to
know if they actually got provided all
of the files on the TMZ 23 when they
actually came in or if this was after
the fact but they said they didn't um
investigate there was no impetus to
investigate because there was no
evidence or compelling evidence or
intelligence was presented so again I I
think they're referring to just the tips
that they got from us and from the ITA
when they decided there was no impetus
to investigate it's it's unclear whether
they got um the full dossier of the 23
positive
tests and so what did Kier say about
it well unfortunately in Kier there's
not one mention of the W inii team being
involved with the timeline that I showed
you or any of the factual or scientific
investigation doesn't seem that they
were involved involved at all and and
that's that's incredible to believe
actually based on The Whistleblower
based on our tips and ita's tips based
on 23 what what more evidence do you
need when you have 23 positive tests for
the very substance that a credible
whistleblower a few months earlier told
you was being used by Chinese athletes
and order to gain a performance-
enhancing
Advantage so where are where are we now
that's sort of the facts some of the
rules some of the science so where are
we now clear clearly we the world needs
answers clean athletes demand and want
answers and deserve answers the public
who are asking these same questions
deserve answers from our from our
stpoint there's a few key points number
one we we still have to get Justice in
the individual cases you know athletes
both the Chinese athletes who never got
the benefit of due
process they deserve to have have the
results management process take place so
that the world can know for sure whether
or not this was legit contamination or
was it something else and and that's why
we're asking for justice in the
individual cases to be done and and of
course athletes that competed against
those athletes deserve to know should
they have had a fouryear suspension and
being kept out of major International
competitions since that time period
or was the no fault finding the right
finding and and that that question by
other athletes who swam against these
swimmers just as recently as the 2024
Parish Olympic Games as well as the 2021
Olympic Games as well as World
Championships and international
competitions in between that question if
if unanswered very well may haunt these
athletes who swam against them for the
rest of their life
and and that's not fair that's not what
the system should be doing and the
statute of limitation the legal ability
to bring the cases has not
expired wada could direct we think still
under that provision article 71 direct
because the results management process
has never happened they could direct
them to be brought and if chinata
doesn't bring them they can be brought
by someone else with jurisdiction and
authority to bring them accountability
has to happen we we have to know why it
took you know whistleblowers assumably
giving information to the media for this
to come out and for the world
unfortunately in the way that it did
find out about these positive test and
the fact that China swept these cases
under the carpet and they weren't
handled according to what the rules were
and then and then of course we need
reform so a little bit more detail we've
asked for an indiv indep dependent
investigator and prosecutor to prosecute
the cases we've also asked for the
disclosure of the file
including a lot of the science data and
all the science data that we've talked
about a little bit here today and in
part if W truly believes that
contamination of TMZ can happen like it
happened in this case well they should
be sending an advisory out and a warning
out they they never did that or other
athletes putting themselves in similar
situations if W to truly believed that
you would think they would take the step
that's what they've done in other
scenarios that's of course what many
natos national anti-doping organizations
do we do it so we give those warnings
stay away from supplements but we've
heard nothing about TMZ and we haven't
seen the data to answer the questions
that need to be
answered we we now know after this broke
it's been reported in the media there
there're more cases out of China where
wada failed to follow the rules failed
to require the Chinese anti-doping
agency to follow the rules two more were
announced on on a swimmer that was in
the 2024 games for a powerful steroid
met TI andone or what's known as dball
that similarly was blamed on some food
um but the cases weren't announced there
was no disqualification there was no
violation um and and and we need to know
how many more are there of these
because those cases are getting special
consideration and treatment under the
rules and athletes from other countries
listen we we have contamination cases we
know that they can exist we go through
the proof scientifically factually to
prove the source to prove the causation
and when that happens we announce it and
we publicize and maybe we give a no fa
finding if it is deserved under the
facts and the science of those
particular cases so we know those happen
the problem here is these have all been
swept under the carpet and the rules
haven't been applied and so the world
doesn't know there's not accountability
on the actual decision making on those
cases and and that's not allowed under
the rules so even if it was
contamination in these cases how many
more are there W has made reference that
there's many
more how many more athletes in countries
are getting special treatment by the
rules and and what are we going to do
about ensuring that there's not two sets
of rules some for for the Chosen Few and
some for the rest of the world that are
actually applying the rules as the rules
are required to be applied and then and
then lastly reform has to occur and and
you'll see in the world Aquatics audit
compliance report that was done they set
up a a panel to review it they have a
list of 10 or so recommendations that
are that are they are fine and are and
are good but I but I think what's really
important is that we don't know all the
reform that's going to be necessary
until we can find out actually how this
happened and why this happened we can
create you know another 2,000 pages of
rules I think the water Code system in
its entirety is about
2,600 and something Pages the water code
the international standards models of
best practice the laboratory standards
it's an incredible amount of legislation
and
regulation we can create another but
2,600 pages but that's not going to get
to the
decision-making and the answers of how
this actually happened and and I think
we think and we've heard from athletes
on this that's what's really important
to happen first before deciding on what
the reform looks like because in a
vacuum you can't answer what the proper
reform is going to be yeah there's ideas
out there and yeah we can come up with a
list of those and we and we all should
but we ought to get to Prosecuting the
cases first and we ought to get to how
and why this happened the accountability
point before we get to what the reform
ultimately might look
like all right with that I'm going to
take some questions here and of course
for anybody uh still with us on the
video you can see my email as well as
our play clean our tip line if you want
to send a question anonymously um but
feel free also you've got my email happy
to answer any questions we can and and
as I said at the very beginning it it
matters because clean athletes deserve
better frankly from the system and and
we're hoping that we can get to the
bottom of what happened and put in place
the accountability as well as um
processes going forward to ensure that
something like this doesn't happen and
so the rights of the Chinese athletes
get their due process athletes who lost
to them are protected and those athletes
that those with positive tests from
China may have competed against their
rights are upheld as well I really
appreciate it Travis great information I
just wondered why um or if you could
speak a little bit more about why the
fena case didn't go forward you had
mentioned that it had been appealed by
Fina yeah no it's a it's a great it's a
great question I should have mentioned
so Fina appealed the case um a few days
later I think it was maybe the 15th they
appealed it of July and then I think it
was the 21st of July they withdrew their
appeal there there's no indication of
what caused them to withdraw their
appeal what seems clear is that their
appe was filed after their science
expert opinion after the legal opinion
but there's no indication of what then
occurred for them to withdraw the appeal
there's a note in the kti report that
says the General Secretary of Fina now
World Aquatics who just had come on U
the job at that time he was new he said
that they based their decision to
withdraw their appeal largely on their
science report which you know they had
interestingly before they appealed so it
seems that wada as W was making its
decision to appeal or not they were in
concert and discussion with Fina and
while Fina appealed preserving the
appeal deadline um they decided to
withdraw it after W decided not to move
forward with their appeal but there's no
specific indication of what came up in
that interim that you know forced them
or made the decision for them to
withdraw their appeal yeah so any more
any more questions yeah I have one um do
we have any uh examples of this kind of
substance in the food supply any other
contamination cases that uh might be
relatable to this yeah no great question
and thanks for it no there's there's no
evidence that this you know shows up in
kitchens or is in the food supply it's
it's a it's a controlled medication
available by prescription in in some
countries not available here in the US
for example um so no there's no there's
no evidence that we're aware of outside
of you know this case that it shows up
um anywhere other than in a via a
prescription medication thank you yeah
thanks um even though Kier was an
external lawyer like he wasn't in he
didn't work with W hadn't he worked with
W at uh in the past um and so there's a
possibility that his report is kind of
tainted because he's not that external
he's an external Source but he's worked
with v before yeah so I don't I don't
think it I don't think he worked with W
but it but I think um what's been
reported is how W found him was that
their auditor called W and said when
this was first coming out and there were
calls for an independent you know review
to be done that W does W's other auditor
who was friends with Mr katier called
wada and said hey if you're looking for
someone here is someone who used to be
you know um in the Swiss legal community
and might be good to be able to do that
so I'm not sure he actually Kier himself
did work for w um but it was a friend of
someone who who who did do work for
w yeah I guess I I guess I'll just
expand slightly on that I mean I think
the I think the Kier and you know let's
assume he has all integrity and um you
know was going to do the right thing if
given the opportunity the problem he
just I don't think it was given the
opportunity you know the two very narrow
terms of um the reference of the
questions that we talked about were so
narrowly focused you know it's very easy
when you hire someone to just put what I
call the blinders in the handcuffs where
they can't really look at what's
happening around these two narrow um so
let's let's assume he did everything in
the right way on those two questions um
it was just flawed from the start in our
opinion it should have been a much
broader um conversation and
investigation to to really find out that
again that broad question I asked did w
to do everything they should have done
CLE clean athletes who go through
everything that we that I describe that
they go through on a daily
basis they want the organizations that
have that are supposed to have their
back to to go to those great links to
protect their rights if they're willing
to go to those Great Links why isn't the
organization willing to go to those
great links to make sure their rights
are protected and seems clear that
wasn't that wasn't done um in this case
based on what we know and it's why we're
asking for for
more all right other
questions yeah Brett uh so a couple
questions for you I I guess first was
there any evidence provided of I guess
the the timeline of the athletes eating
like what meals did they eat at the
hotel when was their last meal to
provide any evidence of when they would
be getting the last dose and looking at
that yeah no listen it's it's one of
those questions that we we don't have
answers to what did they eat how much
did they eat when did they eat all those
things um May maybe they're there in the
file we we just we just we just don't
know we haven't seen it so it's in part
why we're asking you know for the file
to be produced to to see if this
contamination um conclusion that W seems
to have made is is actually you know
supportive by the facts and the evidence
okay and then second question I guess uh
the Val Eva case was uh I mean her her
defense was it was food contamination
how is this different yeah I think I
think same in that they were the same
substance lowlevel 2.1 is what we
understand in in her case she claimed
contamination um different procedures
and outcome and W's handling was totally
different she ended up they appealed it
to the court of arbitration for sports
she ended up getting a four-year
sanction even though she claimed also
contamination now you have to look at
the facts to see what are the real
differences in the case but the handling
of those were starking only different
from W's perspective even though there
were a lot of commonalities between them
all right
Allison so you mentioned um swimmers
earlier in the presentation and we've
heard from athletes and sers from around
the world and of course here in the US
what can you tell athletes right now in
terms of next steps and what can be done
now moving forward yeah no well Alison
thanks and obviously you know Olympian
on our team runs our um athlete
engagement international relations so
thanks for for the question and listen I
I I think you saw my slide about Justice
and trying to prosecute the cases it's
the statute of limitation which is 10
years has not expired and we're asking
and and advocating for an independent
prosecutor that has an investigative
group has to be separate from W because
at this point wada is you know wed to
this contamination Theory despite all
the questions that exist around it so it
has to be outside of that but we're
asking the W executive committee to
engage an independent investigator and
prosecutor and actually get the case
File do the factual interview the
athletes look at past test results
determine whether they stayed at the
same Hotel all the things that we've
talked about and and then bring those
cases so that we can get before you know
the court of arbitration for sport and
and so that the world can have
confidence that um these cases have been
hel handled the right way and that
Justice whatever that is if the athletes
ultimately get a no fa case because of
legitimate contamination that is what it
is or is there another sanction that
should be put in place and and look I I
think this is maybe the most important
question because that's the question
that will as I said earlier will haunt
athletes potentially for the rest of
their lives what opportunity was taken
away from me um and it will remove any
dark cloud from the Chinese athletes and
it's it's terribly unfair that those
athletes had to show up in Paris with
this Dark Cloud hanging over their head
and and that's due to the fact that the
rules weren't followed if the rules
would have been followed and they would
have been announced and everyone would
agreed it was no fault contamination
that dark cloud wouldn't have existed
people may have debated it but it
wouldn't have been near as tragic for
for those athletes as it turned out to
be in the Paris Olympic Games as far as
going forward and I think this is a
really important question athletes have
to keep doing the right thing and we
would beg you yes we understand how easy
it is to get frustrated by this
situation and want to just throw in the
towel and say forget this whole
anti-doping thing it's not working but
we're but please don't do that that's
not the right outcome the right outcome
is to engage use your voice use the
power that you have to help us and
others both our governments from around
the world National anti-doping
organizations from around the world the
sport organizations from around the
world to ensure that this system best
protects clean athletes rights and
doesn't allow certain athletes from
certain countries to get the special
treatment that we saw in these cases and
so there's a number of ways get in
contact with us if you're interested a
number of ways you can Advocate and
actually engage to get the type of
program and and reform to the system
system that we need to ensure that your
rights are ultimately upheld the the
alternative is not the answer you can't
just throw in the towel and we can't
just throw in the towel and it's exactly
why on behalf of you as a clean athlete
and you as an Olympic swimmer Allison
know this we're pushing we're pushing
hard to get the system as good as it can
be to ensure that athletes have an
opportunity to clean to win the right
way and win the clean way so
thanks all right well listen thanks
everybody I think we're going to have
lunch here I want to thank everybody at
home for joining us through the video as
well and and look the idea here was just
um given how much there's been written
about this topic given as I talked about
at the beginning how important this is
um we know it's tough to read everything
and we've our team here has been doing
um the job to try to follow it all
because we know how important it is to
our athletes and we're getting calls and
questions you know literally daily from
our athletes about this scenario and and
what can be done and how are we going to
to move this forward for the good of
their rights to compete on Level Playing
Field and so we were hopeful that you
know this brief conversation and I'm not
necessarily trying this case in this
presentation at a court certainly not
the scientific expert I've obviously
consulted with all of them but we
thought it would be just an opportunity
to kind of have a conversation go
through the facts see the outstanding
questions and some of the reasoning that
has gotten us to this point and also
most importantly see where we need to go
to um restore the confidence in the
global anti-doping system that athletes
um you know deserve and and actually are
demanding us to be able to do so thanks
for watching and hope to see you
somewhere um around the us or around the
world so thank you
[Music]